h
uh
[Music]
oh e
am I audible now am I audible am I
audible hello hello
hello I think I should be audible
now let me see am I audible am I still
not
audible yes yes it's it's okay now yes I
think I am finally audible some kind of
setting had to be changed so once again
welcome back to the asket show episode
whatever it is
216 and I hope you're all doing great
and it's great to see you all I'm going
to take questions from the live chat
today the questions that you will ask me
now in real time and let me see who all
is there on the live chat I can say
geopolitics enjoyer Surendra Gupta
Mahendra Pratap Kumar vishwajit Malik
Arjun Patel B Kumar deab Bonia Ganesh
sen starlord Matrix ashaad Shivani
maheswar om Miker hello Rahul yadav
trupti patil blue three shvi Kahan
barwad satwik Jau hello
sir good to have you here Rohit rajput
scientist Muhammad ismile feminist
Slayer ashaad python gaming samarpan
Singh Guru Muk mayank masani aavad sorab
Sinha uh sunit RI om deshmuk yavan
yashan p chag Sharma famous talk let's
see nature uh Prashant DOI gopath bisra
Alvin Rodriguez nabanita Das
geopolitical dub hello V try Slayer Nel
ra and everybody else okay okay I'm
gonna stop greeting you all as always uh
we can start taking questions John V Jal
McLovin and so many
others so we'll start with the questions
but before I take the questions I'll
address a a question that people have
asked lots of times and I get this
question question a lot of time in the a
lot of times in the in the in the
comments in the live chat as well as to
why have I switched off why don't I use
the super chats why don't I enable the
super Chats on this channel and the
answer is very simple a lot of my
viewers are students and students can't
afford to pay money to ask to to have
their questions answered I have been a
student myself I haven't forgotten how
it was when you're a student you broke
more or less unless you're really
fortunate so and I don't want to create
a situation where I start taking money
to answer questions I think that is a
that's not for me I'm sure there are
lots of other channels that do that good
for them it's that's not the kind of
thing I do okay so I will never take
money to answer questions I will I will
not treat people differently based on
whether they can pay money or not
everybody is the same absolutely no
super chats if you want to contribute
something there are other options to
contribute I think there is super
something else or I'm sure you can
figure it out if you if you want to it's
not important okay so yeah that's the
point uh so I hope that addresses that
particular question that many people
probably
had okay questions questions Muhammad
ISM says could you provide an update on
the current situation in Ukraine and
offer insights into the potential
direction of the ongoing
conflict okay so what's happening
there's not much movement on the map
right usually when you have a war that's
ongoing in which one nation invades
another Nation you can changes you're
going to see lines on the map changing
right the the current what whatever the
current Battlefront is whatever the
front lines are those lines keep
changing and territory exchanges hands
and and so on so uh let's go to the map
of
Ukraine of the of the region since we
are dealing with geopolitical issue so
here is the map we go towards Ukraine
and uh so this map that you see over
here on the screen it's not it doesn't
represent what's really happening on the
ground
uh Crimea you can see is now part of
Russia Russia has retaken Crimea that
happened in 2014 that's old news and
when it comes to uh Russian advances in
Ukraine they certainly have taken the
luhans Don donet regions which is the U
Eastern parts of Ukraine Mario pole I'm
sure and so on they haven't moved on
Odessa yet and they are kind of on the
south southern uh Bank of the nier river
when it comes to the Kon the city of
Kon uh and that's the kind of situation
we have and uh it's kind of a frozen War
situation now okay there isn't much
happening of course the war has taught
everybody else a lot of lessons on what
as to what kind of Technologies are now
going to be employed on the battlefield
in 21st century Battlefield so when the
war started you had a certain set of
weapons that was being used tanks and
all the you know standard
weapons but as the word progressed the
Weaponry changed now you have lots of
drones that are being used loitering
weapons Ling Munitions suicide drones
kamikaz drones the shahad 2 drones there
are anti-personnel drones that are being
used there are mind fields that have
been laid all over the place it's a
disaster of course it's a disaster from
a humanitarian perspective from a
civilian perspective it's an absolute
disaster okay uh but the lines on the
map aren't changing much now there are
battles going on and
it's it's low intensity Warfare and
there are missile strikes happening the
Russians are are striking at various uh
well Ukrainian positions including
mercenary positions in which you may
have fighters combatant from other
countries apart from Ukraine North Korea
seems to have entered the frea in some
in some way on on the side of Russia
Ukraine is also hitting out at Russia in
some way or the other drone strikes or
or missile strikes there is the question
the big question that's on everyone's
Minds right now is whether the Americans
will allow the ukrainians to use long
range Strike weapons such as long range
missiles you know 100 kilometers plus
range missiles that that's medium range
short to medium range but yeah in the in
the context of this war it's long range
and and the Russians have said Mr Putin
has said that if the ukrainians use long
range missiles that are or or weapons
that that are NATO weapons then we're
going to treat that as well as as a as a
red line and we reserve the right to
retaliate and respond through means
necessary which kind of tells you what
it means right so there is always a
danger of escalation okay this is a
proxy war it's a proxy war between
Russia and the West Russia and NATO NATO
is owned by the US so it's essentially a
proxy war between Russia and the US the
proxy is Ukraine and the other the first
level of the proxy is Ukraine the second
level is NATO okay NATO isn't directly
involved it's indirectly involved and uh
and so on so that's the situation it's a
frozen conflict to to a large extent
it's a slow War scenario not much is
happening right now it has the potential
to escalate very
rapidly and Russia is very content to
wait as long as it it needs to to
achieve its objectives the objectives
are the densification of Ukraine and the
demilitarization of Ukraine and Ukraine
becomes a neutral uh nation and uh no
longer poses poses a threat to Russia
the kind of threat means what do we mean
by that it means becoming a either a
member of NATO or a proxy of NATO which
it currently is so Russia eventually
would want to effect a regime change in
Kia get rid of Mr zinski and get
somebody else a pro Russia person in
place and they would say that that's a
neutral government and perhaps the
territories of Ukraine will will change
forever the map of Ukraine will change
forever that's a
situation um not much movement on the
map happening right now but it is a very
dangerous flash point when it comes to
the global geopolitical order there's
the potential for very rapid unforeseen
escalation that could happen any
time uh so it's it's one of the most
dangerous uh situations that we are
currently facing in the world right now
that is overall the situation uh nothing
much more to say apart from
that okay okay
now um Surendra Gupta says why does
India have a very small number of
diplomats you mean the ifs Indian
Foreign Service has approximately I
don't know what 2,000 diplomats roughly
gave take 1700
diplomats and yeah that's the way it has
been that's the way it has been since
the Cold War since since the 28th
century and we have we are continuing
that Legacy I mean it makes sense to
augment the number number of diplomats
we have we need to have diplomatic
missions everywhere in the world
wherever we have interests as a nation
national interests uh so uh if you if
you take the example of Nations like the
US they they would have in excess of
10,000 diplomats maybe more than 20,000
diplomats when it comes to China the V
they would have a diplomatic core that
has a strength in the vicinity of 10,000
Russia would be this would be similar
Singapore is far ahead of India in in
the number of its diplomats diplomatic
uh for some reason India continues to to
hold on to its nhuan
Legacy uh it does make sense to induct a
lot more diplomats especially young
people especially people from various
backgrounds not necessarily uh
necessarily people who have come through
the upsc course uh the upsc uh route uh
you need diplomats who have
specializations in various Fields not
necessarily have gone through through
upsc you can obviously give them some
training you need people who uh whose
core competence is science it's physics
Nuclear Physics chemistry bio technology
you need people whose core competence is
history that's the history of a certain
Nation or a certain region let's say
German history or let's say Appalachian
history or let's say the history of the
Sahel region of Africa or or the history
of China you need to have people who are
who have deep specializations in such
things in such domains very desperate
domains you to bring them into the
Diplomatic core that's what a that's
what a nation does in in order to pursue
its interests to the fullest extent and
India doesn't do that so it's it's
rather strange and curious that after 10
plus years of Mr Modi being in power we
still are kind of in on the in the
same we still have the same situation I
don't know why why it persists I mean is
it so hard to affect reforms within the
government I I don't know so if you ask
me it beats me I don't get it we need to
have more diplomats of course you see
every Ministry does engage in diplomatic
activity okay let's say uh you have the
ministry of Commerce trade and commerce
okay you do trade deals with various
Nations there are trade deal NE
negotiations going on with various
Nations across the world Australia the
US the EU UK whatnot what are those
negotiations that's diplomacy and the
Indian Foreign Service won't be involved
in that the ministry officials will be
involved in that so that's also
diplomacy so actually if you look at it
that way we have a much larger Corpus of
people who engage in active diplomacy
but the Indian foreign surveys
technically if you just look at it from
that perspective is quite small but we
have all these Ministries that have
their own uh individual Outreach
diplomatic Outreach and diplomatic
efforts and activities in various um
domains that does happen but it does
make sense to induct a lot more people
into the Diplomatic core people from
like I said lots of different diverse
backgrounds who have specializations in
things that are that would really you
know give teeth to our diplomatic
activity so that's the kind of thing
that should happen but we're not there
right
now
okay um
Shiva rally says what was there in
Southern India when in the north there
was the Indus Valley sarasti Hindu
civilization okay let us go back to to
the map and try and understand the
situation so this is the map now our
history textbooks our history teachers
your history TT teachers will tell you
that there was something called the
Indus Valley civiliz Civilization or
haran civilization and it was mainly in
in Western Northern India India okay
that's what they will say now let me
explain this to you in case you are new
to the channel or you've not heard me
say this before that this was not some
separate civilization that existed and
disappeared the so-called Saras Indus
Valley Civilization or harapan
civilization which should actually be
called the Saraswati Hindu civilization
or Saras Sindu phase of our history it
was not some separate civilization and
some other people who lived there and
the
vanished it was a certain phase of our
history okay us as in all of India the
entire subcontinent plus which includes
the people of Afghanistan Pakistan even
Iran the whole of the subcontinent
Bangladesh everybody you get the point
this was a phase a certain time period
limited time period of our history our
history goes back 10,000 years minimum
and the oldest era of our history is
where you have the what the historians
called the preh harapan phase or
whatever okay and we know that this this
okay so we know that this uh uh so this
civilization or this phase of our
history was an urban phase of our
history and this entire region the
Saraswati synu region or the this
so-called civilization that existed
there its geographical extent uh was
greater than Egypt plus Mesopotamia put
together gigantic huge monstrous okay U
the boundaries were essentially see it
included parts of Afghanistan much if
not all of Pakistan some parts of
easternmost Iran Gujarat Rajasthan
harana Northern India all the way to
madh Pradesh and parts of Maharashtra
huge geographical region and what we saw
in this region was complete
standardization of weights and measure
the same language the same symbols the
same culture and all of that which is a
continuation and and that culture still
continues today the cultural ele
elements that you see in that era of our
history are still visible today a lot of
them similar Gods the same yoga poses
the same mangur you know so the the
red the red red pigment that ladies put
on their in their in The Parting of
their hair the same Bangles and the same
story of the of The Crow and the Pebbles
and and so much more okay so um
pashupati worship Shiva worship bull
worship all of that so we still have
elements of that in today's today's
Indian Society even though it is now
eroding away very rapidly but just like
India Today is an
interconnected Nation even back then the
whole of the subcontinent was
interconnected now our historians and
archaeologists have not done enough
to uncover the archaeological history of
Southern India and Eastern India that's
why we don't know much as to what was
going on in Southern India and Eastern
India during the time period of the S
during the sarasti snu phase of our
history of course now we are discovering
sites like kiladi and and uh much more
but it's it's just baby steps that we
are taking so we are unfortunately
facing a lack of archaeological EV
evidence and data right now a lot more
needs to be done to uncover the
interconnections between between the
various regions of the subcontinent
but just like today the whole
subcontinent was
interconnected and uh the brahmi script
is found even all the way down south in
in places like K and whatever other
places we have I forget the names right
now in Tamil Nadu in in Telangana Andhra
Pradesh Karnataka the the the the brahi
script right right which is u a more
standardized form of the Saraswati synu
script so we have that everywhere but we
are facing a dirth and shortage of data
points and and evidence so the ASI needs
to get its act act together and and and
bring out more evidence more
archaological evidence but I assure you
that the whole of the subcontinent was
interconnected and the they have the
same culture all over the place in
different forms of course very different
forms our culture manifests itself in in
a variety of different ways some of
which look very different from each
other but it's still the same culture if
you go deeper so that's what I can say
we need to do a lot more archaeological
work which is not happening for whatever
reason uh but yeah hopefully someday
probably during our lifetimes hopefully
it will happen and we'll get to know
more all right
okay let's talk about the Western Asian
region Israel and Gaza and all that so
the question is by Shivam what will
Israel do next after Yahya do you think
they're going to attack Iran they did if
they do attack Iran then will Russia be
involved in this matter will Russia get
involved in this and British says will
Russia support Iran directly if Israel
goes to war with
Iran right okay that's a question so
what's going on uh that that latest
terrorist was killed recently um Yahya
his name or whatever his name is the the
Hamas boss he was taken out by a tank
tank shell and so on um so what we
seeing is is is the the decapitation of
the leadership of Hamas by Israel they
they're doing a very effective uh uh job
at completely taking out the the
leadership structure of of
Hamas uh and they have also obviously
completely terrorized Hamas with the
pager attack and all that those remote
control attacks so it's it's like Hamas
is on is is very much on the back foot
right now and hamas's biggest supporter
is obviously Iran Iran is a nation that
punches way above its weight it is a
nation that is geopolitically very
ambitious very active it has proxies all
over the Middle East Western Asian
region Western Asian
region and so on and Iran as we know
regards uh two Nations at as its
greatest adversaries with good reason
first is the US United States Iran calls
the United States Shan eorg the great
Satan and I well the Americans have
imposed sanctions and all kinds of
things on on Iran since essentially
1979 and the people of Iran have
suffered tremendously as a consequence
it's Siege Warfare in in the modern day
so one can understand why they consider
the Americans to be so evil and
America's number one supporter or or
supporty whatever you want say is
Israel uh and Iran considers it to be
its number two enemy or or
interchangeably number one the Zionist
regime they call it right uh and
Iran perhaps by now probably is a
nuclear weapons power there was that
anomalous earthquake that happened
somewhere in Northern Iran which is a
region where you typically don't have
earthquakes cor four or something on the
RoR scale which is very strange so I I
personally consider Iran to be the 10th
nuclear power now and that's a problem
for Israel because Israel is an
Undeclared nuclear power and it used to
be the trump card now if Iran also has
nukes then it's a big problem for Israel
and the whole deterrence scenario
changes drastically so
uh and we have had all these tensions
between Iran and Israel those drone
strikes missile strikes the latest
missile strike happened not too long ago
about 200 missiles were launched by Iran
on Israel and a lot of them hit their
targets and a lot of them carried rather
small payloads Warheads conventional
Warheads but that kind of sends a signal
and they were able to bypass the iron do
Iron Dome system that Israel has which
is one of the most sophisticated
anti-missile ballistic missile defense
systems and so on and recently just a
two or three days ago
Iran hit Mr netanyahu's residence with a
drone strike and we're not sure if Mr
nanyu was there not or not but it's a
direct attempt assassination attempt on
the prime minister of Israel so look
with all this as the
context it's it's pretty clear that isra
is going to respond in some way sometime
soon or sooner or
later recently there was a leak out of
the Pentagon clearly there's some kind
of mole inside the Pentagon but the the
Israeli plans to attack Israel to attack
Iran where kind some of some portion of
that was leaked out a couple of pages of
thing so I think they're going to attack
Iran at some point in time at a time and
place of their choosing like you say you
know like they say uh so the question
now is
if the Israelis launch a significant
attack on Iran the question is is Israel
going to do this alone or will the US
also be
involved if the us is going to be
involved it's going to be involved from
the sea aircraft carrier strike groups
is the US confident enough that it can
take on
Iran from an aircraft carrier Iran has
excellent missiles so there's a whole
lot of questions out there in the open
but let's say Israel attacks Iran in
some way air strike missile strike
whatever what happens then
uh they could Target Iran's nuclear
uh development sites where its nuclear
weapons program is being developed
cilian civilan nuclear program whatever
it is is being developed you know it has
various nuclear installations and and
sites those could be
targeted
uh that could happen and even the
Iranian leadership could be targeted
taret inan because they tried to Target
Mr Netanyahu so T forat that sort of
thing could happen the question is what
happens if Israel does this if if they
attack Iran will Iran be on its own or
will there be some kind of Russian
involvement Chinese involvement is our
more or less out of the question because
uh the map tells us the map tells us
that China is way too far away for to be
able to uh take any real action okay
okay but Russia isn't too far away it's
it's just uh let's say
about well less than 500 kilometers away
Russian territory from Iran so and Iran
has been supporting Russia in its uh
special military operation in Ukraine
Iran has been supplying Russia with
drones had two drones and various other
kinds of Weaponry so one can expect some
kind of quid proquo from Russia Russia
is in the process of selling a bunch of
sophisticated fighter planes to Iran I
think the Suk 57 which is already the
latest one they have the fifth
generation one and uh is it the Su 57 is
it Su 35 I'm not sure which one but it's
going to be selling a bunch of pretty
good fighter planes to Iran uh and maybe
it may get involved in some way in the
defense of Iran if Iran is on the back
foot so it's all speculation right now
but I would expect some kind of Russia
involvement in some manner if there is
an attack on Iran from Israel but
obviously this is all speculation I
don't have the real intelligence the
real evidence as to what is being
planned but it makes sense strategically
and logically for Russia to come to the
aid of Iran Iran is an important asset
for Russia and China to have in the West
Asia
region if Iran Falls or or get defeated
then it completely changes the power
dynamics in the region the geopolitical
balance of power and it gives the United
States and Israel and the West a
tremendous upper hand in this region and
the Strategic uh fact or agreement that
China has signed with Iran becomes null
and void a 25 year old 25 year strategic
agreement in which China is going to
invest at least $400 billion worth of
money into Iran in exchange for large
quantity very large quantity of disc
counted energy which is petroleum more
or less mainly so Russia and and China
need Iran to continue to exist and and
remain strong in the region so I think
from that perspective it makes logical
sense for both of the nations in some
way or the other to come to the aid of
Iran and Russia is much more in a
position to be able to do this at short
notice so probably some some kind of
involvement from Russia will happen
especially if Iran goes on the back foot
that's what I think will
happen Okay class says will an East
Asian conflict start from North Korea
instead of China North Korea blew up its
Bridge with South Korea and they're
sending soldiers to Russia China could
use North Korea like how Iran uses its
proxies well I think it's I imagine it
would be pretty common knowledge that
North Korea is a is a Chinese
proxy that that I think is known should
be known to everyone North Korea is
not uh an independent Sovereign Nation
it is a proxy of China it's a wasal
state of
China just like South Korea is a vasal
state of the US just like Japan is under
the US occupation and a vasal state of
the US North Korea you could not you I
would not say it's under Chinese
occupation but it is very deep beh hold
into China and it depends on China for
so many things without China North Korea
probably can't
survive uh North Korea has gone through
tremendous hardships because of Western
sanctions they have faced starvation
they have faced all kinds of
difficulties there have been terrible
humanitarian crisis in North Korea but
they have resolutely stood firm one
could say it's kind of like the Chinese
terminology of the way the Chinese right
and speak but they have been supported
by China they have had this barter
system with China which is allow owed
them enabled them to survive and for
China North Korea is a very valuable
asset in the region uh in the Korean
Peninsula region it kind of offsets and
and balances out to some extent the US
presence in the
region uh and it's kind of uh the Joker
in the pack it's the unpr predictable
dangerous uh actor Kim Jong-un the Kim
family you know nuclear weapons they
have they have very good long range
missiles that can strike C
well the us if they want any part of the
us even the east coast of the US so
North Korea is a very good proxy and
asset to have for China and you're right
there are tensions right now that are
ongoing between North Korea and South
Korea I'm not sure if there's a conflict
that's going to emerge from here but as
you can see North Korea can threaten
South Korea as well as
Japan even even Tha Taiwan through by
its missiles it's it's Marines its Navy
Etc so North Korea has a reasonably good
Navy they have a very large number of
submarines way more than India and they
have good missiles longrange Miss
missiles icbms intercontinental
ballistic
missiles so right now we are seeing
tensions between North Korea and South
Korea is it the standard routine saber
rattling that happens from time to time
just to remind South Korea that you
are that that we are that you are our
enemy and you are under threat
uh or is it something
else one hears recently that Mr Xi
Jinping president she uh instructed here
his his uh one of his missile regiments
to be ready for war and all that once
again that could just be rhetoric one
doesn't know usually if you're going to
if you're planning for war you don't
Telegraph it to your adversaries in
advance you keep it quiet and you always
see Warfare is all about deception like
sunzu said so when you're able you
should appear to be unable when you're
unable you should appear to be able when
you're strong you should appear to be
weak and vice versa so this could be
another set of deceptions we don't know
what's really happening but the Korean
Peninsula is one of the dangerous flash
points in the world there number of
flash points right now this Ukrainian
region Ukraine region Ukraine war that's
a very dangerous flash point the Korean
Peninsula is a dangerous flash point um
Taiwan is a flasho India Pakistan is a
flash point India China is a flash point
these are the some of the FL flash
points in the world and North Korea
South Korea is obviously an unresolved
conflict it's it's a state of Cold War
active Cold War uh no ceasefire so yeah
it's dangerous and it's certainly a
region that uh if not managed properly
could
potentially um lead to some kind of
warfare
yeah mcloven says why isn't Elon Musk
trying to Launch starlink in China if he
forces starlink in India wouldn't it
also be a threat to China can we use
China as a proxy to fight this
war
okay I'm sure Elon Musk must have made
some kind of proposal in the past to
China uh and requested the Chinese
leadership to allow Starling to operate
there as as a token gesture just to put
it on the record everyone knows China
will never allow Starling to operate in
their country it's a national security
threat for China to have foreign
internet foreign foreign internet
provider beaming the Internet Straight
to Chinese homes and Chinese people
wherever in China it's it's a national
security threat China has this great
firewall by which by which they they
they very strictly and rigorously censor
the kind of information that's
accessible to its population and
Starling would completely bypass that
it's a disastrous danger for China and
China obviously will never allow that
because they are a self-respecting
Sovereign Nation China right and the US
is their greatest adversary isn't it so
China won't allow it now I'm not sure if
Elon Musk has in the past requested
China or not I expect he would have at
some point in time made such a
request just to put it on the record
that yeah I did it in China as well now
the point is so it won't work it won't
work the point is what about India he
wants
to have star to offer starlink in India
now we know that price-wise Starling
doesn't make any sense to any Indian we
have some of the some of the cheapest
internet in the world cheapest
high-speed internet in the world okay we
in India we are actually very fortunate
as a nation that we have such high
quality internet throughout most of the
country at such incredibly cheap rates
okay it's not being beamed to us from
the from space from orbit but it's it's
your local you know the cables and all
that but it it works really well it's
really high speed high
quality and it's incredibly
cheap the the price per megabyte or
gigabyte will be like incred incredibly
low compared to any other Nation we can
think of now if starlink starts
operating in India they're going to
provide you limited internet
at at a much more expensive rate so most
Indians won't care for it w buy it some
people rich people may buy it just to
show off that look I've got Starling
that's it but here's the deal and by the
way sorry here's the deal Ros are saying
oh sorry I'm not Biden the point
is the point is you know there are we
have problems in India right every
nation has problems we have problems in
India we have a very large population of
foreign infiltrators who is living in
India close to maybe 100 million
Bangladesh's ringas Etc and these
elements can be uh can be leveraged by
foreign powers to unleash Mayhem in
India riots in such situations now let's
say you have a hypothetical fictitious
scenario okay in which you have a riot
in some particular part of India some
City some town or whatever what the
government will immediately do is they
will shut down temporarily
uh the cellular Networks phone cell
phone networks and internet in that
region and then they will go out on the
street the police and they will pacify
the situation essentially and once
things go back to normal in a few days
the cellular network and the internet
will be restarted so that's the kind of
uh action the government takes when
there is some kind of disturbance in
some in any part of India now imagine
you have starlink which is beaming
internet to all parts of India in that
case
in that case even if the government try
shuts off the cellular and internet
networks in the region starlink will
keep beaming internet to that region of
course the government can tell starlink
please switch off your signal to this
particular region starlink may or may
not
comply okay they may or may not comply
or they may comply 24 hours 48 hours too
late by which time the anti-national
elements the riot ERS will get enough
time to do whatever they want to do
despite there being no internet in the
region from other
sources it can allow terrorists and
separatists like like Pakistani
infiltrating in Pakistani terrorists
operating in Jammu Kashmir that region
or cookie terrorists operating in in in
Manipur missam or other terrorist
whoever it is the nites in other parts
of India it will enable these people to
operate with impunity to communicate
with each other despite whatever
internet or cellular bans the government
may put in
place that's why it's a disaster if you
allow starl in
India and Elon Musk has gone on the
record in the past okay he is an agent
of Empire Elon
Musk um let me go and find that
particular tweet for
example uh Elon musk's tweet let just
give me a minute I'm going to dig it out
very fast as soon as I
can um Starling there was a controversy
on Twitter a few days ago I I was kind
of involved in that because I
expressed um the opinion that starlink
is dangerous for India just give me a
second let me let me pull it out as soon
as quickly as I can Elon musk's
statement
um here you have it okay let me put that
on the screen okay okay so let me put
that on the screen this is what I
tweeted on the 17th of October today's
20 right here we are so Elon Musk had
tweeted this in in September
2021 so it's it's in response to
somebody okay
uh so a certain Naval intelligence
officer Lea kohistani told CN that she
would love it if SpaceX would just flood
Afghanistan with starling so that
there's a way for us to maintain
communication with our Afghan Partners
which tells
you that starlink if it is beamed to any
part of the world you can communicate
over there you don't need ground
stations even without ground based
stations with which amplify the signal
even without this station star link is
accessible it'll give you a certain
speed maybe one or two MVPs which is
enough so then
uh uh so somebody says Scott Manley that
they need to find a friendly neighboring
country
who wants to help the us against Taliban
so that they can deploy a downlink
station Elon Musk says our satellites
launching in the next few months 2021
September our satellites launching in
the next next few months have inter
satellite laser links so no local down
link needed an active in 46 months
probably that is way back in 21 so it's
already active
now and then somebody else asks him how
does transmitting into a country without
local downlink work on the regulatory
Sky regulatory side Elon Musk says they
can sh break their fist at the sky which
means that they can't do a thing and
even if they take regulatory action and
ask us request us to stop beaming the
signal they can keep shaking their face
at the sky we will not stop it if we
want if we don't want to and at some
other time Elon Musk had said that we
will coup whoever we want we we we we
will coup whoever we want we can do a
coup he's happy to for his country to do
a coup in any nation that that as as
suits the US
so my point is this is a very dangerous
thing Starling and I hear that the
government of India is considering
allowing Starling in India and giving
them uh
spectrum that I think would be a
disastrous step for National Security
and I would like to urge the government
of India to not allow starlink in
India okay don't allow starlink in India
it will give all kinds of anti-national
elements um a free hand in communicating
with each other so what what had I said
at the
time uh yeah let me put this back on the
screen okay not
this uh I had said this just two or
three days
ago starlink if made available in India
will pose a grave threat to National
Security it will give separatists riers
Etc unfettered internet access will
render the government of India helpless
India should not allow starlink in do
you see Elon Musk asking for starlink in
China and I'm pretty sure he must have
asked at some point for starlink in
China just to put that request on the
record so that they can you then you
know tell India Nations like India that
you need to allow it in you are
democracy China is not they use all
these tactics against us my point is
Starling should not be allowed in India
can we use China as a proxy to fight
this war how how on Earth do we use
China as a proxy we can't if if start is
arounded in India how is it a threat to
China it is in no way shape or form a
threat to China it's a threat only to
India
right so yeah that is the
deal karat says is Iota negative or
positive number Iota is a Greek letter
of the it's a letter of the Greek
alphabet it can be whatever you want it
to
be it's it's just a variable right Iota
it's just a variable like X is a
variable or Y is a
variable in know programming if you're
if you're writing code you can assign
any value to a variable so Iota is just
a letter of the Greek alphabet and in
physics we use a lot of the Greek
letters to denote various
variables in Shing as equation we use
use the letter s right denote the wave
function so Iota can be whatever you
want it to be positive negative
fractional zero whatever you want it
doesn't have any specific uh
meaning om deshmuk said says North Korea
recently has sent 12,000 soldiers to
Russia to fight against Ukraine do you
think it would accelerate the war to
Nato Nations to send their soldiers also
Well the West can use this as the
pretext and the justification for
allowing soldiers of other nationalities
to fight the war against Russia in
Ukraine yes it can certainly happen why
did Russia have to do this I'm not
really sure why they allowed North Korea
soldiers to fight in the
war probably the conflict is now
expanding in its scope very
slowly this is uh the defining conflict
of the first half of this Century it is
the conflict that has ripped open the
the the fissures that kind of existed
and were papered door between east and
west and uh now we are seeing this the
the the battle lines or the sides the
confrontational sides being drawn very
clearly on the one hand you have the US
and its entire menagerie of wasal the EU
NATO um various African nations it it
U neoc
colonizes the auk US grouping the
various Nations it occupies like Japan
South Korea ET this entire grouping of
Nations is the West let's say so it's
not a geographical entity it's a
geopolitical entity it includes Nations
like South Korea and Japan which are
under us occupation since 1945 or since
the 1950s in South Korea's k is so all
the all of that is the West that's one
side the other side is the East which is
Russia
China North
Korea
Iran
Syria
um Lebanon perhaps Yemen to some extent
and certain African nations so on and
for us India we are kind of in between
we neither here or nor there or we are
kind of the bridge between east and west
and we we are staying neutral as as long
as we can that's the situation so with
this as the context maybe Russia wanted
to get North Korea involved in this
North Korea as we know is managed by
China it is a Chinese proxy Chinese
wasal so it it probably was done at
China's beest this sending of 12,000 or
whatever number of soldiers in Ukraine
it will give them exposure to an active
conflict you know uh it always
helps a military force an armed force to
be uh
involved in war fighting on a reasonably
regular basis because otherwise you're
just doing War gaming in tactics and
strategy on the on the white board or
whatever and you're not actually exposed
to Warfare you're not you're not being
shot at fired at and you're kind of
rusty so 12,000 soldiers from North
Korea go and fight for a certain amount
of time in Ukraine they're going to get
gain a wealth of experience tactic
strategy Battlefield the battlefield
scenario is and so on and they can come
back and
and you know propagate their learnings
throughout the North Korean
military so maybe that's the reason why
it was done but yes it can certainly uh
serve as the justification for NATO to
send soldiers of various other nations
to fight the Russians in Ukraine in in
case Any Nation volunteers to send
soldiers so yeah it it could lead
to uh a
broadening of the
conflict okay ainash abinash aara says
is it a possibility that Indians living
in Canada might be deported back to IND
India so that cannot happen to Indian
origin Canadians who are citizens of
Canada but there's definitely a large
number of Indians who are working in
Canada who don't have Canadian
citizenship they may be on various kinds
of visas other student visas or work
visas or or whatever and yes the the
relationship right now between India and
Canada is is pretty bad all thanks to
one person Justin
trudo um
and I don't think it has reached the
bottom yet I think it there's there
there's more to
come and we haven't seen the worst of it
yet that's the feeling I get okay so a
lot has happened right uh India withdrew
its Ambassador and and six or so of its
diplomats from Canada so we just have a
bare minimum staff now at the Indian
Embassy in Canada and India also
expelled six Canadian diplomats
including the top six which are the top
six diplomats including the High
Commissioner acting
Ambassador so this was a pretty drastic
move that India did and then later the
Western press tried to spin it and said
that Canada expelled six Indian
diplomats it's not the case that's
that's a lie that's complete fabrication
that's propaganda India first withdrew
the diplomats Indian diplomats we then
expelled six Canadian diplomats and then
the Western media started to started
spinning the story around but that is
what has happened and there's been a lot
of
acrimony the entire Canadian government
has been involved from top to bottom in
making statements against India
including the Prime Minister the Prime
Minister Mr tro made a deposition
against Canadian Parliament or whatever
it was some kind of committee in which
he had to admit that he has no evidence
that supports his claims of India doing
whatever and Indian diplomats being
involved in in allegedly involved in
some illegal activity or he has
absolutely no evidence of it he says
it's it isn't evidence it's it's
intelligence intelligence is words it's
hearsay it's not
actionable evidence it's not evidence
that can stand scrutiny in a court of
law so he's bluffing his lying he's
prevaricating his absolutely outright
lying he's been caught lying he's been
caught
red-handed now
things make it worse I mean the question
we to ask ourselves is
why have the Canadians chosen this time
to do this and what are they trying to
achieve by nuking their relationship
with India India won't suffer
economically Canada will suffer
economically from
this okay if especially if India stops
doing trade with Canada it's not going
to hurt us it's going to hurt them it's
a smaller economy they they
import many important things from
India and it it will affect them badly
at least it will hurt them to some
extent it won't hurt us now why are why
is Trudeau doing all this he started
this entire business about a year ago
when he came to the G20 Summit in Delhi
right and uh he made some allegations at
the time that India had India was
involved in in in bumping off some some
rag tag third rate terrorist Canadian
terrorist of Indian origin a terrorist
who had tried to immigrate to Canada
illegally using forged documents and he
was still given his his his Visa request
was denied twice at least but eventually
he ends up getting citizenship and he's
a terrorist a Canadian terrorist of
Indian origin so all that happened now
why now why suddenly all of this now I
think look Canada is is a member of the
G of of the of the five eyes Coalition
which the US and four of its Clos vasal
the US Canada the UK Australia and New
Zealand the five anglos [\h__\h] Nations
English speaking
Nations now the five eyes are the
closest allies of the US the closest VES
and it's in these five nations that most
anti-india elements are harbored and
given Refuge a number of anti-india
separatists and terrorists are US
citizens a large number of this these
khalistani terrorists and supporters and
sympathizers and separatists are
Canadian citizens there's a significant
presence of these elements in the UK and
Australia as well maybe to some extent
in New Zealand as well maybe to a
smaller extent New Zealand is very small
population wise so these nations are
used by the US to prod and poke and and
and pressurize India in a variety of
ways whenever
required and it is impossible that
Trudeau would take such actions without
the explicit approval of his of his boss
loses in Washington
Maryland so I think this is a pressure
tactic used by the US uh the US has been
ever since the Democrats came to power
the US has been after India 2020 onwards
uh especially after 22 February 22 when
India refused to condemn the Russian
military operation in Ukraine and India
remained neutral and we have been buying
Russian oil ever since in very large
quantities so we haven't cowed
and pressed our forehead to the ground
in front of the feet of the West we
haven't done that we have stood straight
and that is a big problem for the west
and they tried their best to interfere
in our elections in 24 and to some
extent it worked Mr B did not get a full
majority he got 240 is which is he's now
running running a coalition government
but he still came back to Power third
successive time um so the ideal scenario
see there are multiple scenarios the
problem the US has with India is that
India is a growing economy
it it fulfills certain criteria India is
a large population the largest
population in the world large land area
with a tremendous amount of resources
that's number two number three the
fastest growing large economy in the
world number four we are soon going to
be the third largest economy in the
world by 2050 will'll be the second
largest economy in the world 2047 2050
and by the end of the century we'll be
the largest economy if things continue
the way they are so that's a big problem
for them they are the existing hedgeman
and an existing hegemon will never allow
a potential hedgeman to emerge they will
root they will nip that in the bud so
that's why they're going after India so
there's a number of ways they go after
India they have a lot of assets within
India people who are compromised we have
100 million roughly foreign infiltrators
who are living in India they can be
activated at any time they want there is
the project cave that's going on Project
cookie land cooki land for Christ an
artificial Christian Nation that will be
that they want to create out of Manipur
mizoram parts of Bangladesh and parts of
Burma then there is East Pakistan that
has been recreated by the Americans
there are all these media Outlets that
they they fund engos that they fund
allegedly political parties that they
allegedly also allegedly fund and so on
so the Americans have so many Assets in
the subcontinent in the region within
India lots of people who are working for
a foreign power and so on there is
industrial scale religious conversion
happening in various parts of India the
Tupa thing happened recently the tup the
temple is
encircled look at look at the map you'll
see it's encircled by
religious uh U buildings of other
religions so we are being we India is
under siege India's culture and
civilization is under siege they want to
appro and wipe it out the best case
scenario for them is for India and China
to go to war and they could induce such
a war if they can and the ideal
situation is that India and China blow
each each other to bits and nothing is
left and then America can focus fully on
Russia that's the best possible scenario
in the short term the second best
possible scenario in the short term for
the US is India and China again go to
war somehow India is destroyed China is
greatly weakened and then the Americans
can once again focus on Russia and take
care of Russia these are short-term best
case scenarios for the US and third best
case scenario is regime change in India
and then they can work on India
whichever way they want the long-term
end game for the US for India is the
anization of
India okay every state becomes a
separate nation uh you can have a
dravidian coalition of nations in the
South that project is going on very very
strongly various other nations Jammu
Kashmir they would like to seced they
would like to see various parts of
Northeast India Far East India become
separate countries every part of India
should be a separate country ideally a
non-hindu country that they can
individually control and then they
can they can uh control the destiny of
these various population groups that's
what the US would like okay and please
understand that they have no hatred for
India there it's nothing personal is
just a business as The Godfather would
say Von is just business business okay
nothing personal don't take it
personally I have nothing against you
it's just business but that's how it
goes that's how you play the game of
geopolitics as a great power is a
superpower uh so all of that is going on
and now coming back to Canada okay now
you understand understand what's
happening so Canada is is is a tool that
they use to apply pressure on India they
want to create a certain image of India
India is a rogue State like Iran or
North Korea you know we we send our
assassins to other countries and and
kill innocent people that's the kind of
image they want to create of course the
Americans can do that they can kill
Osama Bin Laden in whatever country in
Pakistan they can kill an Ali in in
Yemen their own Citizen and his teenage
son they can kill whoever they want
wherever they want that's okay they have
the right to Israel can kill whoever
they want various terrorists in various
parts of the world with with impunity at
will I'm not saying is Israel should not
they should there is no place for
terrorism in the world so it's okay to
do that but India cannot touch
terrorists who are after India we don't
have the right to do that and their
media will ensure that they paint India
in a very horrible light so all of that
that's the that's what they're doing
they want to make Modi look like a
dictator they want to put him in the
same league as Kim Jong-un and Putin and
Shi Jinping or maybe even worse than
that you know make him look like a worst
case scenario compared to these guys and
they want to make India look like a like
an intolerant
backward um Nation with backsliding
democracy democracy and and lack of
religious freedom and all that and using
by creating this image they can then
justify whatever they do with India
maybe a regime change maybe
balkanization whatever so that's what
they're doing so Canada is being used
for that now the relationship between
India and Canada may get worse and yes
uh the can Justin Trudeau recently in
the deposition he said that India is is
he alleged that India is behind you know
shootings and and God knows what kind of
crimes in Canada
so it it looks like he's setting the
stage for accusing random Indian origin
people of being terrorists and being
proxies of the RW
ranw especially holders of Indian
passport so it may happen it may happen
that people in India people in Canada
who are of Indian origin with Indian
passports may be jailed maybe prosecuted
with criminal may have criminal cases
thrown against them and the easy the
lightest thing that could happen is
deportation back to India something much
worse may may happen which is
imprisonment in Canada for God knows how
long so yeah things are bad and things
could get even worse between India and
Canada that is the situation right now
overall India is going to face
increasing heat from the West in the
coming
years it's going to not it's it's it's
not going to be easy for India it's
going to be very tough for the
government of India for for for Prime
Minister Modi the Americans the West may
try to affect regime change as in
bringing the coalition government down
perhaps by inducing certain Coalition
members to with support or whatnot so
many things are possible they have so
many Tools in their
toolkit so it's going to be a tough road
ahead for
India I think it's going to be almost a
miracle for this government the Modi
government to stay in power till 2029
and uh yeah India is going to face a lot
of heat a lot of pressure from the
west and let's let's see how things go
the Chinese are currently in the process
of sweet talking
India uh the Chinese Ambassador and the
embassy in India are putting out very
flattering statements every day multiple
times a day the global times which has
been strident anti-india for decades it
is putting out
rather benign statements about India and
so on the Chinese are trying to sweet
talk India so that's a whole different
question and different issue but yeah
it's part of the overall context in
which we are discussing these
matters
okay Stone says is isra actually an ally
or friend of India or is it like some
other Western Nations wasal please
answer this I'll tell you something my
friend friends Israel is nobody's
vasal Israel is no one's
vasal maybe Israel has vels but Israel
is no one's wasel understand that okay
I'll tell I'll tell you that first of
all second what's the relationship like
between India and
Israel
well reasonably good but there are
problems every nation every Rel ship has
problems okay but the relationship
between India and Israel is reasonably
good but it is it would be mistaken for
Indians to believe that Israel is
India's number one Ally or or or India
is Israel number one Ally what is an
alliance first of all an alliance is
something that is based on a treaty a
treaty between two Nations or multiple
Nations that you that you sign with very
explicit Clauses as what you mean by
Alliance one example of an alliance a
military Alliance is that if some
between two Nations is that an attack on
one nation will be considered to be an
attack on both Nations and whichever
nation is attacked the Other Nation the
Ali is Duty bound an allian bound to
come to the military aid of the nation
that is attacked whether it's Nation a
or Nation B both ways that's an alliance
that's the military Alliance and
economic Alliance is all about econ
economic cooperation India and Israel
have no such treaty no such Alliance so
don't use so we have to understand that
the word Alliance means something very
specific in geopolitics you cannot use
that word Loosely or
lightly India has no treaty allies
anywhere in the world we don't have any
Alliance treaty with anyone with any
nation in the world India has no allies
and India is an ally of no Nation
okay we can use terms in diplomacy like
friendship and and all that and shared
values and all that's that's nothing
it's it's wague it's wague nothingness
it means nothing okay so India and
Israel are not treaty allies we don't
have any Alliance treaty we have no
treaty as such so there is no alliance
between the two Nations friend there are
no friends in geopolitics okay there's
only National interest if you have
shared interests and a convergence of
interest between two Nations then the
two Nations will work together and if
there is a Divergence of interests and
and if there is a conflict of interest
then then two Nations typically will be
adversaries and they may go to war so
that's the situation in geopolitics
let's be let's be very clear about this
okay
now so India and Israel have a
reasonably good relationship um when it
comes to voting in the United Nations
India often abstains on various uh
resolutions votes for Resolutions either
against or in favor of Israel India
often abstains from these
things um and India has had a very long
history of supporting the Palestinian
cause and even the current government is
Mr the the Modi government has
reasonably good relations with uh the
Palestinian Authority or whatever it is
okay so India is on both sides kind of
but the stronger relationship is clearly
with Israel Mr Modi was the first Prime
Minister of India to ever visit Israel
and he has a good relationship with with
Mr
nanahu uh and there's a lot of military
cooperation that's happening between
India and Israel the Barak missile is a
jointly developed missile between the
two Nations and U and there's some kind
of past history as well during the
cargil war when the Americans refused to
supply ammunition to India the Israelis
stepped
in that sort of thing but we also have
to remember that Israel
originally wanted uh a great
relationship with China and the
Americans stopped them from doing that
so Israel kind of pivoted towards India
because India is a huge market and it's
a huge market for Israeli exports of
various kinds Israel is Hightech uh
Nation there is that there's also the
question of uh Pakistan so that that's
kind of complicated but let me put the
map on the screen and explain what I
mean by the question of Pakistan
okay where's the map here's the map now
let's This is complicated so pay
attention people see India's greatest
adversary which is clear from the map is
China we know that but historically the
people of India always regarded Pakistan
as India's number one adversary and
Pakistan is still India's number two
adversary right historical enmity
between India and Pakistan and Pakistan
has acted as a US proxy and and the
Americans have funded and financed
Pakistani terrorism in India for decades
in the past so Pakistan is one of
India's great enemies now
Iran
is is a nation that shares the border
with Pakistan the old India Iran Border
is now the Pakistan Iran Border and Iran
is a Shia Nation Pakistan is a Sunni
Nation Pakistan is a US wasal Iran is a
US enemy which means Iran and Pakistan
can never be on good terms Iran and
Pakistan are adversaries stated or
unstated but they are adversaries and
recently we had certain tensions on the
border and the killing of terrorist and
shooting of missiles and all the firing
of missiles and so on so so forth so
Pakistan and Iran are enemies okay now
do you know that my enemy's enemy is my
friend you must have heard of it who is
Iran's number one enemy in the region is
so Iran's enemy is Israel Iran's enemy
is Pakistan so Pakistan and Israel
should be on the same side right the
question for Israel to answer is where
does Israel stand Vis
Pakistan because Pakistan
is a Us wasal in the region and Israel
and Israel's number one supporter is the
US so it makes sense from the logic of
strategy that Israel Pakistan and the US
are in the same
camp correct so then the question to and
and you know Pakistan and Israel don't
have official diplomatic relations but
we know that there have been black back
Channel contacts ongoing contacts
between the two Nations the question is
where does Israel stand on the issue of
Pakistan and then there is the other
question okay which is this let me put
this on the screen now now does Israel
recognize the territorial Integrity of
India now if you look at Israel's
official
Maps they look like this I mean this is
a tweet by me from October 3 this year
which is about two and a half weeks
ago so this is a map that isra an
Israeli website had There's the link
over here and in which you they show
Kashmir P all of that as part of
Pakistan and Ain as part of
China and I tweeted this India stands
with Israel but does Israel stand with
India and I pointed out the incorrect
map of India and soon enough the
ambassador of Israel responded to this
the next day morning he said that it's
it's a it's a mistake by the editor of
the website and the map has been taken
down so let's take a look at the map is
it taken down one
second okay so if you open that screen
that particular link it shows it's a
broken page in the construction whatever
it means in Hebrew I don't know how to
read that so and it's it's not the only
incorrect map of India that you will see
on Israeli websites I just pointed out
one link I can assure you there are more
and those may still exist you may want
to look into it so the the point is this
we have a good relationship with Israel
it works both ways okay and the people
of Israel if you see the polls op polls
and all they seem to have a reasonably
favorable impression of India many of
them and in India people are crazy about
Israel
there are people in India who put up
Israeli flags on their on their social
media profiles right so Indians most
Indians most Indian nationalists and
Patriots worship Israel like like hero
worship most Israel Israelis are kind of
ambivalent or slightly warm towards
India so it's an unequal
relationship now my perspective is very
clear the only flag you should have on
your profile is your own I would never
put any other nation's flag on my
profile but it's up to you Indians are
very emotional people and Indians don't
have a lot of
um they we not taught how to think
critically right so there is that so the
relationship is
good it isn't
perfect
um both Nations could do better towards
each
other uh there are question marks when
it comes to Israel about certain matters
for example there is the terrorism
ongoing cookie terrorism Manipur there
is a subset of the Kookie population
that has become Israeli citizens they
claim that they are a lost tribe of
Israel even though they eat
pork and the Israeli government has has
given them citizenship and there has
been support for the Kookie terrorism in
Manipur coming in from certain certain
segments or subsegments of the Israeli
population maybe the cookie origin
individuals but is it only limited to
that or is there something bigger within
Israel so these questions I think the
government of India needs to take it
take them off with Israel or the
government of India needs to look into
so I would say there are no friends in
geopolitics overall the relationship
between India and Israel is very good
the problem in India is that the people
of India are starved of role
models we are starved of real
heroes we have no real heroes we have no
real role models to look up to and hero
worship so we look outside the country
tell me which great politician in the
past 100 years do you feel is worthy of
reverance and hero worship maybe n
anybody else can you think of anybody
today you can't think of any can you
think of any great thing India has done
the kind of thing Israel has done in the
recent past taking out the whole of the
Hamas leadership wiping out so many
Hamas terrorists with pagers the kind of
things the audacious things they do
India never does that so in want to be
proud of of something they want to they
want to see somebody as a hero and
there's nothing within India that's
worthy of being a hero so what do
Indians do they'll hero worship certain
Bollywood actors who will play the play
certain heroic roles and they will think
that actor himself is that heroic even
though he's just acting or they will
hero worship certain
sporting athletes as if they are Gods
they're not or they will hero worship
other nations like is
my simple point is I understand why you
feel this way but please be
pragmatic please think
critically the
only Ally your nation has is you the
India has no allies outside of India
nobody's going to come to help India if
something goes wrong no one's going to
stand with
India full supports are nobody's is
going to say that to us we are on our
own so overall the relationship between
India and Israel is good but there are
issues okay there are
issues copile talks about Cricket is
Dale stay the greatest test bowler ever
considering his record not only on B
bouncing and receiving conditions but
also in the subcontinent I'm remember is
havoc and nagur 201
10 I would say he's one of the best of
all time let me see okay um
let's let's let's Google this I'm sure
we can find it
somewhere um where's
Google okay uh let's see the
highest Wicket
takers test
Cricket okay so it's going to give you
this Crick info thing now let's take a
look at the test record of Dale stain so
he's played 93 test matches
uh he's got 439 wickets that's a lot the
average is 20 less than 23 and the
strike rate is shocking it's 42
incredible if you look at the top
whatever 20 plus there's nobody with
that sort of a strike rate
42.3 and the next one is wakar yunes who
is all the way down here with
43.5 so when it comes to strike rates
Dale stain is in a class in a league of
his own
very low average and if he did not have
all those injuries he would have had way
more wickets now look at Ashwin I think
ashin is one of the all-time greats so I
would say Dale stain is definitely one
of the greatest ever in terms of strike
rates he's one of the most devastate
probably the most devastating bowler in
the top 20 Wicket takers in the world so
clearly one of the greatest alltime
greats but personally my favorite the
one I thought was the greatest was ctly
Ambrose in his PE he was unplayable and
and if you look at let's take a look at
Ambrose where is ctly Ambrose he's going
to be somewhere around here 400 plus I'm
sure he had there we have it average of
20.9 good God okay strike rate wasn't
that good because later the West Indies
pitches were became like Indian
pitches uh but yeah Ambrose was
incredible when it comes to the average
there's nobody who comes close to him
apart from Glenn
mcra so yeah my favorite back in the day
was Ambrose I wish I had an Indian
player who who I could have idolized but
there was no great Indian fast bowler C
there was a fast medium bowler at best
great bowler for sure but not that quick
until Shad there was no one I could see
who could really hurt the opposition but
Shad was a
very very gentlemanly player very good
guy so yeah uh stay one of the greatest
ever for
sure okay we have de built with starlink
now let's take this Kanan bakara says
France is helping India with 100%
transfer of technology for jet engines
and development of nuclear attack
submarines is it a significant blow for
the US can this development prompt the
US to act against India
in Canadian the Canadian scenario
look France says France has offered 100%
transfer of technology for jet engines
and so on the devil is always in the
details
okay there's always going to be some
Clause somewhere that says that okay
this 0.1% technology will there's always
going to be some fine print okay it's
it's almost Unthinkable that a nation
would give up its hard earned technology
hard it takes so long to develop
technology they would give it up so
easily they of course France has a big
axe to grind against the US okay France
hates being part of NATO France hates
being part of the EU or at least part of
NATO because you are under us domination
France is the only nation in Europe that
still has some kind of a quasi
independent foreign policy they have
their own independent nuclear deterrent
like nobody that no one else in Europe
does the UK doesn't have an independent
nuclear DET okay the big red button
isn't there in London it's in Washington
DC the
button which which um is connected to
the uh
British missiles those missiles are
American missiles by the way so France
is the only nation with somewhat of an
indifferent foreign policy now the
Americans have let's say shafted France
multiple times the Australians were
supposed to buy French submarines the
Americans forced Australians to kill the
deal and buy American submarines that
will be delivered in what 2087 or
something 2030s 2040s 10 20 years from
now so that has really really
uh angered the French clearly no doubt
um so the French would certainly want to
work together with
India and and do something that
displeases the Americans and of course
if it helps the French financially why
not why not do that so I'm sure India
will be willing to pay good money for
this technology the question is will we
get the full technology full 100% to I
think we going to have to be very
careful that we are not uh we don't end
up with 98% technology and that that
will be like crippling okay even that 2%
if you don't have it it can [\h__\h] you
and it can render you completely
dependent on a foreign
power um there is that so the jet engine
is a critical piece of technology for
India we
anyhow need jet engine technology I
don't care how we get it we buy beg
borrow or steal it we need that jet
engine technology without this jet
engine technology our Tes fighter
program is useless right now we are
having to buy American jet engines and
now they're trying to delay that the
Americans are trying to put pressure on
India by delaying the the delivery of
jet engines so we may have the airframe
everything but no engines and what the
hell do you do with it right um
so we it would be great for us to get
this technology 100% to but that may
take decade or two who knows if we
negotiate properly and we ensure
everything comes our way but yeah that's
that's where we are or we could develop
our own coverage cover jet engine the
cover jet engine is kind of underpowered
but it does work so why doesn't India
develop a fighter plane design with two
engines instead of one and put two c
engines
the question is how long do those
engines last and all that but yeah if if
it is giving you a 70 kilon kind of
output thrust then put two so you have
140 K and that's good enough for a
fighter plane I think the Rafal has that
sort of configuration two jet engines um
so that can be a stop Gap measure
measure but ideally we would want to
develop our own homegrown jet engine
that can take time 10 20 30
years so that is a that so the IND ous
jet engine development cannot stop we
have to keep on pushing forward with
that in the meanwhile we if possible get
the French technology that would be
great uh nuclear attack submarines uh
we'll see about that the the main uh
once again it's about the the the
propulsion right jet engines is
propulsion nuclear uh the miniatured
nuclear reactor in a submarine that's
also propulsion it's all about
propulsion so U the Russians and they've
been cooperating with us in in
miniaturizing nuclear reactors and we
are using that in one of a couple of our
submarines the arihant and the Ariat or
whichever the second one is so the
arihan has been operational for some
time and we have a newer one now that
recently became
operational which is more powerful than
the
arihant and each successive iteration
will be better in some way so we are
kind of testing our way iterating our
way to better technology when it comes
to submarines nuclear submarines now the
French offer us good
technology we should go for it as long
as it is once again it's a 100% transfer
of
Technology uh so if all of this goes
through the jet engine technology
transfer the nuclear submarine
technology transfer if all of that does
indeed go through properly 100% it's
something that will greatly displease
the US and if we are making moves in
that direction along with the French
excuse me
then yes the Americans will be tempted
to maybe punish India and France in some
way whether it's through Canada or
through uh separatism or cookie land for
Christ or or religious conversions or or
Farmers protests or some other protests
or or whatever or you know what's
happening these days dozens of bomb
threats against Air India
planes okay somebody's orchestrating
this worldwide who I guess uh who who do
you think is doing this I wonder I will
not Venture a guess because I have no
information but from the pattern and
from the current context in scenario who
do you think is after is behind
this you think it's some stupid
teenagers from within India are making
prank calls you can spoof a call from
within India from anywhere in the world
so I think there's a concerted
U uh effort going on to put India Under
Pressure so yeah if if India and France
goe with this I think both Nations could
be punished in a variety of
ways Muhammad ismile says could you
discuss the German Tiger tanks used
during World War II their effectiveness
and whether they can be confar compared
in any meaningful way to Indian tanks
okay that's an interesting question I am
no expert in tank warfare in the various
tanks we had the Panza
tanks um that the Germans developed very
good tank they were used in the North
African campaign irn r was the the
commander of that and you had the tiger
tanks and the Tigers were really good I
believe but um as for the specifications
and how they compare with current tanks
and previous tanks I'm not sure I'm the
right person for that uh I have not
studied this in detail but the Tigers
were very effective very effective I
mean there's a
whole there's a whole
song by by by Pink Floyd when the Tigers
Broke
Free it's about uh
it's about Roger Waters and and what
what his father went through he was part
of the royal fusiliers company 3 and he
was at the Battle of the anzio bridge
head when the Tigers Broke Free and they
took his life yeah so the Tigers were
very effective but I am not sure I'm the
right person to ask this how do we
compare those their characteristics and
specifications with u with current the
the current crop of tanks that we have
yeah but interesting question
definitely
ah okay sidar Singh R purit says who
could possibly win a fight between
Anderson Silva and Jon Jones J Jon
considering both of them are in the
prime Anderson Silva was he a light
light heavyweight was
he uh Jon Jones used to be light
heavyweight now he's a proper
heavyweight he bulked up for for two or
three years and he fought a couple of
matches and then he got injured and he's
is on the way to recovery I believe now
Anderson Silva used to be a light
heavyweight or was it middle weight I
think light
heavyweight um
israa was in which weight class I think
middle weight okay whichever weight
class it is assume both are in the same
weight class who would win it's pretty
difficult Jon Jones was a stone called
killer as a fighter he defeated almost
everybody if I'm not mistaken I think
he's got an almost unblemished track
record and John Jo and and Silva in his
prime could not be taken out by by
anybody unless he got too overconfident
which may have happened at least
once uh so who would
win difficult
question um
perhaps yeah that that's I think it
would like 50/50 perhaps Silva may win
Perhaps Perhaps but yeah it's a
hypothetical like like what would happen
what would what would have happened if
India had never been colonized that sort
of question but I think Silva would
probably win he was really
wiy uh
yeah mclen says have you read mine C is
it worth reading which publisher the
best version I at some point in my life
I had a cop of Mind camp and that's I
Tried reading it about 20 years ago I
must I may have gone through maybe a
chapter or so and at that point in time
it made no sense to me I could not
comprehend what he was trying to say and
I gave up and I I gave that book away to
someone or something like
that maybe um it may perhaps be more
compreh comprehensible today perhaps I'm
guessing so I've tried reading it a long
time ago I gave up on it but it may
perhaps have a different kind of uh
effect this time or if I if I ever try
to read it again I'm not sure which
publisher is the best version I'm not
sure if it's even available anymore in
India I'm sure you you can go out in the
on the streets and find a reused version
or a pirated version but I don't think
it's available on Amazon or whatever as
far as I can
recall um yeah so I I I don't know which
publish is the best version but I I'm
sure it's a it's an interesting piece of
hisor literature to kind of give you an
insight into the minds of one of the
well major historical figures of the
first half of the 20th century certainly
interesting from an academic
perspective uh geopolitical du says
which nation is more important
geographically bhat or Russia well to
answer that question we'll have to take
a look at the map right so here's the
deal and by the way I'm not Joe Biden so
first let's take a look at bat bat is
located in the southern region of
Eurasia okay and Barat dominates the
entire Indian Ocean region it it goes
all the way deep almost close to the
equator all the way into the Indian
Ocean and it dominates the region and uh
so that gives it a
tremendous an almost god- gifted
geographical location okay and uh it is
a very
large
nation and because it has such a large
land area you will have a tremendous
amount of natural resources that you
will find within this land area whether
you know it or not whether you have
searched for them or not you may have it
you will have it lithium and coal and
gas and petroleum and diamonds and
things that I am saying that you may not
even know right I mean petroleum do we
really have much petroleum in India I
think we've not looked for it enough I
think if you go offshore off the coast
of India you may find more petroleum
that you have in the Arabian region but
maybe it's a good idea we're not doing
it right now ha so yeah geographically a
great
location now if we look at Russia Russia
is enormous
gigantic uh and it goes all the way to
Alaska I mean the ddia island
they they connect the they are the
border between the US and Russia the
small Damia Island over here that's USA
the big one is Russia right so Russia is
enormous and that obviously gives it a
tremendous geographical
advantage I would
say the nation that is more important
geographically is the nation that has
the larger land area and the larger
amount of resources and that is clearly
Russia
Russia has
unlimited oil gas
coal various Metals
uh uh whatever you want Russia is
anarchy everything that you need to run
a country is available all those
resources raw materials are a are
available within Russia itself it
doesn't need to import anything it is a
net exporter of everything when it comes
to India we have to import a lot of
things right so Russia is more important
geog rically but the problem with Russia
is that it is all the way North in
Eurasia and it is kind of cut off from
the warm oceans of the world it has
access to the Arctic Ocean the karasi
the baren Sea The Sea of
OTS and the Baltic Sea and Baltic Sea
yeah and there are all these choke
points that kind of cut off Russia's
access to the open oceans whether it is
the Sea of Japan the Sea of OT the baren
sea
or where the Baltic Sea wherever that's
a problem so it's one ail's heal is its
lack of access to warm Waters and a lack
of uh warm water ports but apart from
that Russia has an incredible geography
and it is gifted in terms of resources
it's complete otari so overall its
Advantage Russia and India has certain
disadvantages in terms of resource
availability okay
okay adwa says why do SUB
Indian experts in quotes consider it
wrong for India to be aless even some of
the retired Indian military personnel a
civilization that truly wants to rise
will never have any allies okay so why
do some experts think of it that way
look I have the highest regard for
military personnel but military
personnel they have one character IC and
that is they look at everything in the
world from the perspective from the
military perspective tactics and
strategy people with a military
background are tremendously good at
tactics and strategy they will look at
the geography they will look at the map
they look at the topographical map of
the region geographical terrain they
will see all the various topographical
features and they can tell you what
tactics to use in this region in this
terrain what strategy to use over a
larger Terrain and so on what they lack
is what most of them lack I would say is
the understanding of deep understanding
of history and culture for example if
you ask a military
personnel about
Manipur and let's say they've served in
Manipur for two years okay they will
talk about the terrain the geography the
jungles the kind of um uh insurgence you
you meet there how ferocious they are
and how evil they are and all that but
they will typically not know the Deep
history of the region and why these
conflicts happened and who are the real
Outsiders who are the real indigenous
people they will not know this many of
them I'm not saying all so that's a
problem
so if you want to understand tactics
strategy battle options all of that uh
military strengths and weaknesses all of
that military personnel are the best to
give you insights in that but when it
comes to understanding
geopolitics I would have to respectably
said that military personnel are
generally not the best at giving you the
right perspective when it comes to this
but in India podcasters and news
channels they will invite military
personnel to talk about
geopolitics it's a shortcut it's a
shortcut the right kind of person you
want to call or invite to to explain
geopolitics is a the person who has
served in the military and is also a
historian will you find such people you
typically won't I have once found such a
person his name is Dr Edward lutwak he
has served in war he has served he has
he has seen action in battles and he's a
historian he's a strategist Dr Edward
lutwak and you will see my podcast with
him on the abijit cha podcast episode I
don't remember which one first 20 25
episodes it's somewhere in there so
that's the kind of person who can give
you a proper perspective which combines
history culture and Military
matters so retired army Personnel
um I don't know what what calculations
go on in their minds they look at things
from a very military perspective and uh
from a military perspective when you are
involved in a military operation you
need multiple companies and you need an
air component you need satellite
component you need Communications you
need Logistics you need multiple
detachments platoons tank tanks infantry
all that so they see that as allies
perhaps that's why they see they think
that in international relations a nation
like India should have multiple
allies perhaps I see it that way perhaps
I'm just speculating to a certain
extent now
historically historically think about
the last 2,000 years of History the
great civilizations and Empires that
emerged in the last 2 3,000 years of
History how many allies did they have
think about the Moria Moran empire did
we have allies yeah we did we had one
Ally the sald Empire salus necator so
yeah so that was not really an alliance
it was a ceasefire the sald Empire The
salus N tried to invade India probably
it was a way of saying hi that I need
some help but there was a brief war and
then there was a ceasefire and then
there was a marriage Alliance and there
was peace after that but it was not a
military Alliance it was an alliance of
Peace okay it was a ceasefire Alliance
and because the two uh royal families
became co-mingled because of marriage so
that can be regarded as as kind of an
alliance but it was not a military
Alliance at all so the morian Empire we
did not have any military Alliance the
Gupta Empire no military alliance with
anybody
Chola Empire we did not have a single
military alliance with anybody else we
had wasal oh yes the cholas had wasal
all the way to the
Philippines so we had wasal we did not
have allies the guptas had wasal yes no
allies the morans had vasal no allies
and so on you can go on um when it comes
to other Empires the Persian Empires the
aid orish Empire they exclusive fought
westwards with the Greeks did they have
allies they had no allies Roman Empire
did they have allies they had zero
allies they only had
vasal the British Empire did they have
allies no they had vasal and
colonies
until okay you going to give me the
example of World War One World World War
I and World War II there was a totally
different period of History which was
the decline and eventually dissolution
of the British Empire or the transfer of
power to Washington
that is a different story but when we
talk about the rise of the British
Empire and it in its Pinnacle and its
Zenith it had no allies it had only
vasal the US Empire today they say they
have allies but those all that the term
Ally that they use they use it for
VES so if you want to rise and be great
you will never have allies you will have
enemies and if you get your act together
you will have vassals and then you can
use whatever language you want to to
describe those Wass you can call them
allies if you want but they're actually
vasal so you are right I agree a
civilization that wants to rise again
will never have alliz it will have
enemies but once it starts winning it's
going to have vasal so what India needs
desperately is to put a few wins in its
belt we need to start winning something
I'm not saying go and capture this
country conquer the territory we need
wins Big
achievements now space station in Orit
around the earth moon landing moon
Colony Mars
colony
or 50 nuclear submarines or or something
of that sort without actually going to
war or maybe a positive development west
of India in the temporary nation and so
on or a positive development Vis A China
and Tibet I mean lots of different ways
of
winning or hosting the Olympics and and
winning 30 gold medals that's a win
India needs to start winning but the
point is as a civilization if you want
to rise again and historically we have
been number one historically that the
past 10,000 years past thousand years
has been an aberration so you want to
rise again you will not have any allies
you'll have everybody standing up
against you and trying to stop you from
rising we going to have enemies and
that's what we are facing now we finally
kind of
rising that's why everyone's against us
we don't have any allies and it's fine
to not have allies why do we need allies
we we are 1.4 billion of us why do we
need allies don't we have each other
isn't 1.4 billion people enough we have
each other that's enough for us we don't
need allies we need to get our act
together raise our standards and start
winning that's what we
need
okay Star
Lord says what do you think about Graham
Hancock and his Lost Civilization ation
Theory and what do you think about the
younger dras impact Theory okay Graham
Hancock is is interesting interesting
guy he says everything dates back goes
back to an ancient civilization only one
ancient civilization that was the root
of everything else that happened that
that exists in the world today that's
the claim he makes and there was this
documentary series that he put out on
Netflix recently
I about a year or so ago I I actually
spent the time and saw every single
episode so he he goes to various
archaeological sites and locations
across the world in the Atlantic Ocean
in South America Mexico um Indonesia or
somewhere he also goes and various the
part in in in Malta
in Anatolia goe and so on he goes to all
these ancient archaeological sites and
it tries to create to to to weave these
these stories together and say that it
all all of these uh were there was an
inch older ancient civilization that was
the originator of all of this and it
tries to point out similarities between
these all things all these things but he
conspicuously avoids
India okay he conspicuously avoids India
we have some of the oldest
archaeological sites in the world in
India for example
over here in the Gulf of kbat you know
kbat the city of the town of kbat used
to be a major port and this region is
called the Gulf of kbat over here you
have an underwater complex of cities it
is not one archaeological site it is not
one town it is not one city there's
entire complex of cities that lies under
and at at the bottom of the Gulf of kbat
and the last time it was
above the ocean was more than 12,000
years
ago during the last ice age so our
ancestors I mean it was obviously not
aliens or martians or or or or or Turks
or Persians who had come here this was
the subcontinent it was our people our
ancestors who built this a complex of
cities with streets laid out in a g grid
structure that goes back 10 12,000 years
before today okay older than goeke and
what not but Graham hanok will stay away
from that
dwarka dwarka a piece of wood from the
underwater city of of dwarka has been
dated to almost 9,000 years before today
so we and then we in Southern India near
puducheri puducheri they discovered an
ancient submer city that could be kavari
pumpum of the suam era that goes back
11,000 12,000 years so we have some of
the most ancient archaeological sites
known anywhere in the world that are
available there are are present in and
around India but griam Hancock
deliberately conspicuously stays away
from this and he tries to go everywhere
else in the world he has some
issue he has some problem with India
okay and when you have a scholar a
researcher who is deliberately omitting
a big giant piece of the
puzzle then you can't take that person
seriously you can't respect that person
if you want to prove a certain thesis
take the entirety of the data into
account and picture but he leaving out a
big chunk is's leaving out the most
ancient civilization known to humanity
so once you see that it's clear the guy
has some kind of agenda he's cherry
picking data and then you kind of lose
respect for the person and you lose
interest in what he is doing so I think
the guy is not a cious
scholar a serious callar will take
everything into
account irrespective of personal likes
dislikes biases racism whatever if if
whether it's there or not okay so I
don't take the guy very seriously and
and he tries he he makes lots of big
leaps of imagination and he reaches
conclusions that that don't really have
a logical sound logical background to
them so some of his stuff is interesting
some of it is in the realm of nutcase
Behavior U but yes his younger D theory
has been Vindicated mostly
um recently uh an impact Creator was
discovered somewhere in Alaska or green
Greenland I think under a thick layer of
ice and that dates back about 11
something 11 point something thousand
years before today which is kind of this
this anomalous event the younger dras
event so it looks like there was some
kind of extraterrestrial impact that
happened on the
planet Comet meteor meteorite not meteor
meteorite that could have um interrupted
the The Ice Age and brought in warmer
weather for about a thousand years or
something roughly so the younger Dr
impact Theory seems to make sense it
seems that there was an impact on Earth
maybe a comet that broke up and
fragmented and hit the earth in multiple
pieces or maybe multiple meteorites that
hit the earth but it looks like uh that
theory uh could be correct so yeah
that's about it
toi says what is your favorite song by
Guns and Roses oh Guns and Roses I wish
they were still active they had lots of
good s good songs what November Rain
and their their cover or their version
of the Bob Dylan classic uh Knocking on
Heaven's Door what else don't cry um
illusion that illusion thing use your
illusion or something they had a number
of great songs the I I think one of the
last great rock bands you had uh Axel
Rose had this incredibly iconic voice
that nobody else could
recreate um yeah so and it it's it's a
band that was at its speak when I was a
young I mean teenager or something so
yeah it was kind of my part of my my
teen years and I kind of missed the days
you know when you had good music uh
today music is just generic P garbage
you know it's nothing uh original about
it unless you go to Indie music and all
but for that you have to really dig deep
so
yeah Guns and
Roses uh Buffalo soldiers says thank you
been thinking about this for a while why
the hell would he not have a single
episode dedicated to India yeah Graham
hancok doesn't make sense he has
deliberately omitted
uh covering the world's most ancient
civilization which has some of the
oldest archaological sites in the world
clearly a guy with an agenda clearly a
guy who is not a serious scholar it's
it's like these Western Scholars who try
to cherry pick their way into the Arian
Invasion migration tourism picnic myth
right same sort of thing guy with a you
can't take such a guy
seriously
okay um
uh pronil says have you seen the synu
Saraswati script decryption it's
fantastic are you talking about the one
by
yam yes ynam has uh
decrypted deciphered the synu Saras
script the so-call harapan or Indus
Valley script
U
and I'm going to bring be bringing you
the details of that in a couple of
months yeah so it's it's it's a great
it's it's a great development we finally
have the decipherment of the synu Saras
script and the language happens to be
Sanskrit unfortunately for those who
have an
agenda karat says why did the Nobel
Prize in physics why was it given to AI
researchers yeah who knows you can't
take the Nobel Prize seriously
anymore the next thing is they will give
the fields medal to somebody
who writes poetry because mathematics
clearly is a branch of literature right
it's a language of
physics I
mean it it really doesn't have any
meaning anymore you know all these
prizes there was a time when the Nobel
Prize meant something and you really
look forward to it eagerly whichever
discipline it was physics
chemistry what else do we have I don't I
didn't ever care about the peace price
it was always a fraud thing but
mathematics and and chemistry you would
look forward to it the economics pricee
sometimes was interesting but these days
you know there's an increasing gap
between the time when the research is
done and when the price is given it used
to be usually you know in the beginning
in the in the first quarter of the 20th
century when all the progress in quantum
mechanics and and relativity was being
done there was typically a gap of five
or six years between the discovery and
the prize maybe 10 years at most
today it's like 30 35 40 years before
you get a prize so Peter higs uh came up
with the higs mechanism in the 1950s or
60s and he got the prize just a few
years ago like more than half a century
later it's ridiculous makes no sense if
someone's doing great work reward them
immediately right or or within a
reasonable amount of time and now you're
not even giving the prize to physicists
you're giving it to AI researchers it's
pointless I mean it just makes you it's
like the Grammys now no one cares about
the Grammys no one cares about the
Oscars anymore the same thing you're
goingon to see very soon when it comes
to the Nobel Prize no one cares
anymore so it's it's overall
um a symptom of the decline of the West
the declining standards of the
West sad to
see sad to see
that okay um
um what else do we
have
uh okay Pras gadway says why has Russia
failed in Ukraine Russia has not
succeeded in doing in in in achieving
what they wanted to achieve why Shi
Jinping told his army to be ready for
war okay one question at a time let's
talk about
Russia um have you heard of the
Peloponnesian
War the Peloponnesian War was a massive
geopolitical conflict that tore apart
the Greek
Islands the Greek
Islands this happened
in roughly 2 and a half thousand years
before today roughly 2,500 years before
today the Peloponnesian War it was
essentially a war between Athens and
Sparta and the Greek historian thides
chronicled the war he wrote a very
important account of the P pelian pelian
War now this
war it lasted more than three
decades so let's say it starts in in
year X okay in year X and two years
after the war or three years after the
start of the war you could say why has
Athens not succeeded in doing what it
wants or why has Sparta not succeeded in
achieving its
objectives and it would be a valid
question and the achievement of the
objectives and the conclusion of the war
was going to happen 30 years down the
line so it doesn't
mean that in year three either side has
failed or succeeded some Wars last a
week some Wars last a year some more
some Wars last 30 years 40
years so if a war lasts 40 years years
you can't look at year three and say
that why has so and so side
failed okay it all depends on a number
of factors the geography the technology
the relative strength of both sides the
overall large scale big picture
geopolitical environment So Many Factors
so this assumption that you are putting
forth this statement that you are making
that Russia has failed I don't agree
with it in the beginning of this uh
today's episode somebody asked me a
different question I said currently it's
a frozen
conflict but Russia has the upper
hand Russia clearly has the upper hand
of course if you read the Western media
and also the Indian media you will get
the you will come to the opposite
conclusion I don't blame you for that
but it is I mean how much Ukrainian
territory does Russia hold about 20% 25%
of Ukraine is under Russian possession
right now you think Russia is
failing really so you have to look at
things
objectively you have to reach your own
conclusions you cannot parrot other
people's conclusions that's called
dogmatic thinking that you use the
results of other people's thinking and
you think it's your own thinking no that
that's not how it works please learn
critical thinking ask question after
question after
question what is Russia's objective what
is Ukraine's objective who is supporting
Ukraine who is supporting Russia is
Ukraine acting on its own or is it is UK
someone's proxy if it is somebody's
proxy whose proxy is it and what does
that big Power
want and what does Russia want and what
has Russia achieved thus far what has
Ukraine achieved this far which side has
suffered more losses which side has more
arms ammunition which side has the more
territorial gains which side has lost
territory if you put all of these things
together ask question after question
multiple questions a string of questions
then you will come and uncover the truth
and the truth is that Russia has the
upper hand and Russia is going to win
this war how can you say Russia has
failed just because they have not
achieved certain objectives as of today
doesn't mean they have failed when I
start running a marathon which is 35
kilometers after if if I am at number if
I in the 20th position after 5
kilometers you cannot say that I
failed you know
understand so please analyze things
dispassionately analyze things using
your own intellect not using the
conclusions presented by your favorite
news caster or news anchor news reader
or podcaster or favorite media Outlet
whichever it is use your own thinking
question them all assume they are all
wrong and try to look at flaws in their
arguments and conclusions that's how you
learn how to think critically without
the ability to think critically you will
not succeed anywhere in life please
please understand this so Russia and
Ukraine are currently involved in a
frozen conflict it's a long War
scenario reminds me of certain Wars like
the pipian War I gave you the example of
it lasted decades but
eventually what happened happened Athens
SP Sparta
one but then
yeah so that was the conclusion of the
conflict but then lots of other things
happened yet Athens a century later
Athens was there again uh so that's how
it
goes
um uh what else do we have lots of
questions okay let's see this one SP
Joker says can Russia again become a
great power and successfully compete
with China militarily if it changes its
Constitution builds military and the US
of withdraws do you understand how much
of a tall order this
is changing its Constitution US military
withdrawal the US has more than
130 permanent military bases on Japanese
soil do you think they will withdraw
from that if you are the world's most
powerful nation and you have in invested
and built
130 military bases permanent bases on
another nation's territory will you just
give it up will you just pack up and
walk away of course you will
not of course you will not the Americans
will never willingly withdraw from
Japan they would be stupid to withdraw
why would they withdraw why would you
give up an
advantage and why will they allow Japan
to change its Constitution why the
Constitution that they wrote for JA it
serves them why would they allow why
would they give up the advantage it's
never going to happen as long as the US
is the number one power in the world
never so the Americans will allow Japan
to build a powerful military if it suits
them they will allow Japan to become
even a nuclear weapons power if it suits
them but all of this will be used only
for America's
benefit Japan can never become a great
power again as long as it is under
foreign military occupation so I don't
see it becoming a great
power in a 50-year
horizon I hope I'm wrong but
yeah
okay uh Martian gamer says update on
isro's new plan they rolled out and also
about their new
ngv
um what new plan have they rolled
out I am I seem to be unaware of it I
mean are they planning to develop
reusable Rockets
no are they planning to uh develop a
rocket that is 10 times most power more
powerful than the most powerful rocket
they have
no are they planning to have a moon
mission human crude Mission To The Moon
anytime soon no are they thinking about
sending a rocket to Mars I think mongan
2 will happen sometime
there's nothing major coming up it's all
small incremental
changes and the government has said
certain things that uh we will have a
space station in orbit around the Earth
by the 2030s yeah great wonderful and
they're going to have humans of the Moon
by 2040 okay good good talk all words
thus
far I am not trying to be cynical here I
hate cynicism but I don't
see any ambition
when it comes to the government of India
for ISRO so ISRO is a government entity
they can
only carry out projects that are
sanctioned by the government of
India let's say you have a bunch of
brilliant engineers in his Ro they all
are brilliant very competent and some of
them IDE have certain ideas of
developing some new technology or let's
say just copying what the SpaceX
Engineers have done reusable Rockets
Rockets whose boost land a
autonomously they may know how to do it
they may have an idea as to how to
achieve this they may even put forth a
proposal to the chairman of ISRO and the
chairman of ISRO may even take the
proposal to the government of India but
does the government of India want this
to happen
no do you see any sign symptom evidence
of the government of India showing any
kind of ambition that ISRO should
develop technology that others have not
developed no we are simply copying what
others have done before they're simply
following their foot steps so I don't
know what big new plan is there okay I
don't see anything exciting anything
challenge it's challenging or space is
challenging for sure so we're going to
have chandrian 4 Chan five or
whatever eventually by the 2040s we if
we are lucky we may have a human Mission
To The Moon we're going to have excuse
me gagan in the next two three years the
first human orbital flight with with
Indian astronauts great I'm I'm happy to
hear that but we are doing what others
have done a long long time ago 1950s
we're talking about
right so
uh that's the problem we have very
talented engineers in
ISRO and the chairman of is say that we
have enough
budget we have enough ISRO has enough
funds to properly carry out all the
projects it is allowed to do all the
projects that have been sanctioned
but what about the projects that should
be sanctioned are not being
sanctioned and even the projects that
are sanctioned we have Sho string
budgets I mean a Hollywood Movie costs
more than the budget of of chandrian or
Mangan right that's how little we have
ISRO the kind of budget ISRO is getting
so I don't know what new plan has been
ruled out I don't know what is
ngv what is NG non let me let me Google
that what is NGB what does NGB mean
let us
see okay ISRO NG LV I Sr o n LV what's
it mean next Generation launch vehicle
let's see what Wikipedia has to say
statutory warning Wikipedia is not
always reliable the the St Parable blah
blah blah blah blah vehicle replace pslv
gslv
lmv3 so lmv3 what is the maximum thrust
all that it has let me see let me see
let me see specification propellent
inertial Mass blah blah Etc maximum
thrust 5150 kons what is Elo Mass launch
mass is this second stage third stage
excuse
me what is the payload it can take
to what is a payload payload maximum
thrust proper Mass gross Mass empty Mass
height powered by burn blah blah blah
blah blah blah blah um maximum thrust
186 something
kilon uh where is the okay come on let
me see let me just search for L EO low
earth
orbit
Leo payload to Leo is 13,000 kilg and
geostationary transfer object 5,000 kg
that is this guy um lmv3 but we are
talking about the other one right
NGB so let me see what is this guy's
payload to
Leo doesn't tell you okay 30 to 70 tons
to ELO and geost station okay this seems
to be a significant Improvement but five
times better to GTO then okay that's
interesting so when will it be
developed it is being developed
currently and blah etc etc when will it
come into when when is the first test
expected to
be list of launches
2031 okay okay that's enough I've seen
enough 2031 Okay so like I said I am not
somebody who likes to be cynical uh I'm
glad this is happening the ngv new Next
Generation launch vehicle seems to be a
significant Improvement on what we have
it doesn't seem to have reusable
boosters and all that which is very
disappointing but it's progress
nonetheless but it's not going to be
able to compete with space SpaceX or
anything absolutely no competition so
okay we are doing some
progress you know you if you give
sufficient funding for new projects that
involve re reusable launch vehicles and
and boosters that can be used multiple
times that can land themselves if you
give the funding I'm sure within five to
10 years our Engineers will be able to
develop something as good as what SpaceX
as has but we are not doing it and
that's what disappoints me the most it
is I'm not disappointed with ISRO with
the chairman of ISRO or the or the
engineers in ISRO I am disappointing
with the entity that controls ISRO which
is the government of India
very
disappointing very disappointing
indeed
okay sidhar Singh rajur says what could
be the possible geopolitical scenario if
this coalition government manages to
remain in part till
2029 the Modi government what changes
will the Modi government
do well I don't know what changes the
the Modi government will do but let me
tell you what changes they should do and
what I would like them to do find a way
to repatriate all the illegal
infiltrators out of
India whatever Bangladeshi infiltrators
we have 50 to 100 million whatever
repatriate them some way or the other
get all the ringas out of India and back
to their Homeland we don't need or want
them here in India and get rid of all
the cookie infiltrators who have
infiltrated into India from Myanmar or
wherever else that is the first thing
the government of India if they can
achieve this by 2029 it'll be like the
most incredible thing
ever that's something India should do
secondly we need to significantly
bolster our Naval
strength okay we need a much larger Navy
we need to especially invest in large
quantities of
submarines in the next five years if
they can somehow acquire or build five I
know it's a long shot what I'm saying
I'm not I'm not naive here but let's say
we increase the number of submarines by
at least five or or or ideally 10 that'
be great at least 100 more fighter
planes and we need to have an arsenal of
at least 10,000 or 20,000 different
kinds of
missiles that's what you need and
obviously keep on growing the
economy at least 7 8% a
year
um and
keep building the infrastructure the
roads highways
um
um Railways new airports highspeed
Railway bullet trains all of that so
yeah all these things need to be done uh
I I hope even even if like a tenth of
that is done it'll be great especially
the eviction of the foreigners so that's
what the government ideally should do to
make India a better place a safer Place
how much will they do I have no idea I
don't know I I hope I'm I'm I'm trying
to be positive here I I am a very
overall very positive person not cynical
person I would like this to happen and
I'm sure the
government can achieve this so let's
keep our fingers crossed and be
optimistic VV says ngv has re
reusability please check okay fine thank
you for that pointer I will check it out
sure I just very quickly went through
the Wikipedia article and Wikipedia
anyway is not that reliable so but I I
will check it out sure surely thank you
for thank you for letting me know I
appreciate that okay let's take a couple
of other
questions Harel mikar says do you think
that if voting exercis is made mandatory
practice for all citizens will it help
in the outcome of Elections would we
have a more stable balanced government
no let me tell you
why what really matters in a democracy
is is not how many people vote whether
it's 50% voting or 70% voting or 98.9%
voting or 100% voting that doesn't
really affect the outcome and the future
of a nation in a
democracy excuse me what really matters
in a
democracy is that every person who votes
is well
informed and they
are
voting uh see democracy fails if the
citizenry if the vote if the
voters
are ignorant
illiterate and misinformed or
ill-informed or
uninformed democracy can work properly
only if everybody is illiterate educated
and really well informed and they have
the ability to think think critically
and properly only then will they make
the right
choice then propaganda won't work on
them and of course they need to be
patriotic you can't have a certain
percentage of the population in in in in
a hypothetical country X where you have
let's say 27% or 32% who are
anti-nationals who have an allegiance
elsewhere I'm talking about a
hypothetical scenario okay I'm not
naming any specific Nation
here you see
that so democracy can work only when the
population satisfies these
criteria making voting mandatory but
half the people are illiterates then
what's the point of the voting those
votes can be
bought or the people can be easily
brainwashed and misled then what's the
point of voting so mandatory voting does
nothing it doesn't affect the outcome of
Elections and it does not help in the
stability of the government or the
country what you need is a fully
literate fully patriotic
and a highly informed population that is
immune to
misinformation and you will never find
such a population which is why democracy
will never work
unfortunately you see that's the
problem John V jwal says please shed
some light on ladak in your position on
Sonam wangchuk son Sonam wangchuk is a
foreign
agent he has deep connection s with
various organs of the West NOS Ford
Foundation uh Muhammad yunos the new
illegitimate regime in Bangladesh all of
that Sonam Muk is a foreign agent he's
acting against the interests of his own
country okay very clear you can look it
up but you will have to do some research
I cannot suddenly on the spot bring all
the different pieces of evidence and
present them here I can't what I will
urge you what I will invite you to do is
do your own research look at the sources
of his funding look at the places he
visits look at the organizations he's
associated with look at the politicians
he is friends with look at the Nos and
and and
organizations outside of India that he's
associated with look at the things he
protests against look at when do did his
protests start what causes was he
protesting against and did his protests
start with the beginning of the cause or
was the problem already there earlier
and what is the envisaged outcome of his
protests and which country
does the in which country's interests
does it work in favor of and which
country's interests do his protests hurt
you have to look at all the these
factors it'll take you time to do this
but if you genuinely interested in
finding out what's happening please do
it I assure you this individual Sonam
wuk is a foreign agent he's working
against the interests of his own country
it is shameful that we have people like
these can be so easily bought out and
they work
for superpowers shameful shameful
really okay
all right uh is there one last question
okay let's see this one sham says why
doesn't ISRO try Landing a smaller
rocket and perfect the technology that
will earn some money more money due to
re avilability while working on larger
rockets for larger payloads payloads
look any project that ISRO does needs to
get a green light from the government of
India it the the
nature of the system is such that ISRO
cannot do a single thing without first
getting return approval
from the government of India the
government of India owns ISRO ISRO is a
is is is is an organization that comes
under the government of India so it
can't do a single thing it can't start a
single Project without explicit approval
and if it says that so and so project
should be started it has to create a
proposal and the chairman has to submit
it to the government the government
bureaucrats and the whole Machinery will
go through it and eventually after a few
months he'll get yes or
no so I'm not sure if such proposals
have been have been submitted
and if they have been submitted well
clearly no progress has happened because
there is no project in ISRO about trying
to get Rockets to land autonomously on
their own you know so it's it's
unfortunate but that's where we stand
today creative hour says are there any
chances of World War II right now it is
the CH the possibility the probability
is low and let's keep it that way okay
all right come on we done with it today
uh thank you very much everybody trti
ptil well let's take one last question
there is two Tire policing in the UK
there are riots every now and then do
you think UK is becoming an Islamic
nation of course the future of UK is
Islamic and uh all the best to the UK
and I would say
congratulations it is what it is they've
done it to themselves so so good for
them it's it's what their leaders choose
so so be it doesn't affect me doesn't
affect us it's their problem it's their
future and they are the masters of the
destiny so let them enjoy it all right
all right uh with this we are at the end
of today's session thank you so much for
so many different diverse questions I
hope I've answered a I think I've
answered a lot of questions and I'm sure
there are many of you whose questions I
could not answer those to those of you I
apologize and I will hopefully take your
questions in the next live session next
weekend I'll probably be in Jaipur so I
will not have a live stream but the
weekend after that we'll be back
so thank you so much and until then take
care keep asking questions keep raising
your standards and I'll see you in the
next session thank you bye